Switching XML descriptor binders

UPnP utilizes XML documents to transport device and service information between the provider and any control points. These XML documents have to be parsed by Cling to produce the Device model, and of course generated from a Device model. The same approach is used for the Service model. This parsing, generating, and binding is the job of the org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.DeviceDescriptorBinder and the org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.ServiceDescriptorBinder.

The following implementations are bundled with Cling Core for device descriptor binding:

org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderImpl (default)
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided DOM API provided by JDK 6. You do not need any additional libraries to use this binder. Use this binder to validate strict specification compliance of your applications.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderSAXImpl
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided SAX API, you don't have to install additional libraries to use it. This binder may consume less memory when reading XML descriptors and perform better than the DOM-based parser. In practice, the difference is usually insignificant, even on very slow machines.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.RecoveringUDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderImpl
This implementation extends UDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderImpl and tries to recover from parsing failures, and works around known problems of other UPnP stacks. This is the binder you want for best interoperability in real-world UPnP applications. Furthermore, you can override the handleInvalidDescriptor() and handleInvalidDevice() methods to customize error handling, or if you want to repair invalid device information manually. It is the default binder for AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration.

The following implementations are bundled with Cling Core for service descriptor binding:

org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10ServiceDescriptorBinderImpl (default)
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided DOM API provided by JDK 6. You do not need any additional libraries to use this binder. Use this binder to validate strict specification compliance of your applications.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10ServiceDescriptorBinderSAXImpl
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided SAX API, you don't have to install additional libraries to use it. This binder may consume less memory when reading XML descriptors and perform better than the DOM-based parser. In practice, the difference is usually insignificant, even on very slow machines. It is the default binder for AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration.

You can switch descriptor binders by overriding the UpnpServiceConfiguration:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {
    
        @Override
        public DeviceDescriptorBinder getDeviceDescriptorBinderUDA10() {
            // Recommended for best interoperability with broken UPnP stacks!
            return new RecoveringUDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderImpl();
        }
    
        @Override
        public ServiceDescriptorBinder getServiceDescriptorBinderUDA10() {
            return new UDA10ServiceDescriptorBinderSAXImpl();
        }
    
    }
);

Performance problems with UPnP discovery are usually caused by too many XML descriptors, not by their size. This is inherent in the bad design of UPnP; each device may expose many individual service descriptors, and Cling will always retrieve all device metadata. The HTTP requests necessary to retrieve dozens of descriptor files usually outweighs the cost of parsing each.

Note that binders are only used for device and service descriptors, not for UPnP action and event message processing.

Custom client/server information

Sometimes your service has to implement different procedures depending on the client who makes the action request, or you want to send a request with some identifying information about your client.

Adding extra request headers

By default, Cling will add all necessary headers to all outbound request messages. For HTTP-based messages such as descriptor retrieval, action invocation, and GENA messages, the User-Agent HTTP header will be set to a default value, obtained from your StreamClientConfiguration.

You can override this behavior for descriptor retrieval and GENA subscription messages with a custom configuration. For example, this configuration will send extra HTTP headers when device and service descriptors have to be retrieved for a particular UDN:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

        @Override
        public UpnpHeaders getDescriptorRetrievalHeaders(RemoteDeviceIdentity identity) {
            if (identity.getUdn().getIdentifierString().equals("aa-bb-cc-dd-ee-ff")) {
                UpnpHeaders headers = new UpnpHeaders();
                headers.add(UpnpHeader.Type.USER_AGENT.getHttpName(), "MyCustom/Agent");
                headers.add("X-Custom-Header", "foo");
                return headers;
            }
            return null;
        }
    }
);

For GENA subscription, renewal, and unsubscribe messages, you can set extra headers depending on the service you are subscribing to:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

        @Override
        public UpnpHeaders getEventSubscriptionHeaders(RemoteService service) {
            if (service.getServiceType().implementsVersion(new UDAServiceType("Foo", 1))) {
                UpnpHeaders headers = new UpnpHeaders();
                headers.add("X-Custom-Header", "bar");
                return headers;
            }
            return null;
        }
    }
);

For action invocations to remote services, you can set custom headers when constructing the ActionInvocation:

UpnpHeaders extraHeaders = new UpnpHeaders();
extraHeaders.add(UpnpHeader.Type.USER_AGENT.getHttpName(), "MyCustom/Agent");
extraHeaders.add("X-Custom-Header", "foo");

ActionInvocation actionInvocation =
    new ActionInvocation(
        action,
        new ClientInfo(extraHeaders)
    );

Any of these settings only affect outbound request messages! Any outbound response to a remote request will have only headers required by the UPnP protocols. See the next section on how to customize response headers for remote action requests.

Very rarely you have to customize SSDP (MSEARCH and its response) messages. First, subclass the default ProtocolFactoryImpl and override the instantiation of the protocols as necessary. For example, override createSendingSearch() and return your own instance of the SendingSearch protocol. Next, override prepareOutgoingSearchRequest(OutgoingSearchRequest) of the SendingSearch protocol and modify the message. The same procedure can be applied to customize search responses with the ReceivingSearch protocol.

The RemoteClientInfo is also useful if you have to deal with potentially long-running actions.

Solving discovery problems

Device discovery in UPnP is the job of SSDP, the Simple Service Discovery Protocol. Of course, this protocol is not simple at all and many device manufacturers and UPnP stacks get it wrong. Cling has some extra settings to deal with such environments; if you want best interoperability for your application, you have to read the following sections.

Maximum age of remote devices

If you are writing a control point and remote devices seem to randomly disappear from your Registry, you are probably dealing with a remote device that doesn't send regular alive NOTIFY heartbeats through multicast. Or, your control point runs on a device that doesn't properly receive multicast messages. (Android devices from HTC are known to have this issue.)

Cling will usually expire remote devices once their initially advertised "maximum age" has been reached and there was no ALIVE message to refresh the advertisement. You can change this behavior with UpnpServiceConfiguration:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

        @Override
        public Integer getRemoteDeviceMaxAgeSeconds() {
            return 0;
        }
    }
);

If you return zero maximum age, all remote devices will forever stay in your Registry once they have been discovered, Cling will not expire them. You have to manually remove them from the Registry if you know they are gone (e.g. once an action request fails with "no response").

Alternatively, you can return the number of seconds Cling should keep a remote device in the Registry, ignoring the device's advertised maximum age.

Alive messages at regular intervals

Some control points have difficulties with M-SEARCH responses. They search for your device, then can't process the (specification-compliant) response made by Cling and therefore don't discover your device when they search. However, such control points typically have no problem with alive NOTIFY messages, only with search responses.

The solution then is to repeat alive NOTIFY messages for all your local devices on the network very frequently, let's say every 5 seconds:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

        @Override
        public int getAliveIntervalMillis() {
            return 5000;
        }
    }
);

By default this method returns 0, disabling alive message flooding and relying on the regular triggering of local device advertisements (which depends on the maximum age of each LocalDeviceIdentity).

If you return a non-zero value, Cling will send alive NOTIFY messages repeatedly with the given interval, and remote control points should be able to discover your device within that period. The downside is of course more traffic on your network.

Using discovery options for local devices

If you create a LocalDevice that you don't want to announce to remote control points, add it to the Registry with addDevice(localDevice, new DiscoveryOptions(false)).

The DiscoveryOptions class offers several parameters to influence how Cling handles device discovery.

With disabled advertising, Cling will then not send any NOTIFY messages for a device; you can enable advertisement again with Registry#setDiscoveryOptions(UDN, null), or by providing different options.

Note that remote control points will still be able to discover your device if they know your device descriptor URL. They will also be able to call actions and subscribe to services. This is not a switch to make a LocalDevice "private", it only disables (multicast) advertising.

A rarely used setting of DiscoveryOptions is byeByeBeforeFirstAlive: If enabled, Cling will send a byebye NOTIFY message before sending the first alive NOTIFY message. This happens only once, when a LocalDevice is added to the Registry, and it wasn't registered before.

Manual advertisement of local devices

You can force immediate advertisement of all registered LocalDevices with Registry#advertiseLocalDevices(). Note that no announcements will be made for any device with disabled advertising (see previous section).

Configuring network transports

Cling has to accept and make HTTP requests to implement UPnP discovery, action processing, and GENA eventing. This is the job of the StreamServer and StreamClient implementations, working together with the Router as the Cling network transport layer.

For the StreamClient SPI, the following implementations are bundled with Cling:

org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.StreamClientImpl (default)
This implementation uses the JDK's HTTPURLConnection, it doesn't require any additional libraries. Note that Cling has to customize (with an ugly hack, really) the VM's URLStreamHandlerFactory to support additional HTTP methods such as NOTIFY, SUBSCRIBE, and UNSUBSCRIBE. The designers of the JDK do not understand HTTP very well and made this extremely difficult to extend. Cling's patch only works if no other code in your environment has already set a custom URLStreamHandlerFactory, you will get an exception on startup if this issue is detected; then you have to switch to another StreamClient implementation. Note that this implementation does NOT WORK on Android, the URLStreamHandlerFactory can't be patched on Android!
org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.jetty.StreamClientImpl
This implementation is based on the Jetty 8 HTTP client, you need the artifact org.eclipse.jetty:jetty-client:8.1 on your classpath to use it. This implementation works in any environment, including Android. It is the default transport for AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration.

For the StreamServer SPI, the following implementations are bundled with Cling:

org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.StreamServerImpl (default)
This implementation uses the built-in webserver of the Sun JDK 6 (com.sun.net.httpserver.HttpServer), hence, it does NOT WORK in an Android environment.
org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.AsyncServletStreamServerImpl
This implementation is based on the standard Servlet 3.0 API and can be used in any environment with a compatible servlet container. It requires a ServletContainerAdapter to integrate with the servlet container, the bundled JettyServletContainer is such an adapter for a standalone Jetty 8 server. You need the artifact org.eclipse.jetty:jetty-servlet:8.1 on your classpath to use it. This implementation works in any environment, including Android. It is the default transport for AndroidUpnpServiceConfiguration. For other containers, write your own adapter and provide it to the AsyncServletStreamServerConfigurationImpl.

Each StreamClient and StreamServer implementation is paired with an implementation of StreamClientConfiguration and StreamServerConfiguration. This is how you override the Cling network transport configuration:

...
public class MyUpnpServiceConfiguration extends DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration {

    @Override
    protected Namespace createNamespace() {
        return new Namespace("/upnp"); // This will be the servlet context path
    }

    @Override
    public StreamClient createStreamClient() {
        return new org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.jetty.StreamClientImpl(
            new org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.jetty.StreamClientConfigurationImpl(
                getSyncProtocolExecutor()
            )
        );
    }

    @Override
    public StreamServer createStreamServer(NetworkAddressFactory networkAddressFactory) {
        return new org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.AsyncServletStreamServerImpl(
            new org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.AsyncServletStreamServerConfigurationImpl(
                org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.jetty.JettyServletContainer.INSTANCE,
                networkAddressFactory.getStreamListenPort()
            )
        );
    }

}

The above configuration will use the Jetty client and the Jetty servlet container. The JettyServletContainer.INSTANCE adapter is managing a standalone singleton server, it is started and stopped when Cling starts and stops the UPnP stack. If you have run Cling with an existing, external servlet container, provide a custom adapter.

Advanced options

Switching XML descriptor binders

UPnP utilizes XML documents to transport device and service information between the provider and any control points. These XML documents have to be parsed by Cling to produce the Device metamodel graph, and of course generated from a Device graph. This is the job of the org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.DeviceDescriptorBinder and the org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.ServiceDescriptorBinder.

The following implementations are bundled with Cling Core:

org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderImpl (default)
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided DOM API provided by JDK 6. You do not need any additional libraries to use this binder.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10ServiceDescriptorBinderImpl (default)
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided DOM API provided by JDK 6. You do not need any additional libraries to use this binder.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10DeviceDescriptorBinderSAXImpl
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided SAX API, you don't have to install additional libraries to use it. This binder may consume less memory when reading XML descriptors and perform better than the DOM-based parser. In practice, the difference is usually insignificant, even on very slow machines.
org.fourthline.cling.binding.xml.UDA10ServiceDescriptorBinderSAXImpl
This implementation reads and writes UDA 1.0 descriptor XML with the JAXP-provided SAX API, you don't have to install additional libraries to use it. This binder may consume less memory when reading XML descriptors and perform better than the DOM-based parser. In practice, the difference is usually insignificant, even on very slow machines.

You can switch XML binders by overriding the UpnpServiceConfiguration:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

            @Override
            public DeviceDescriptorBinder getDeviceDescriptorBinderUDA10() {
                return super.getDeviceDescriptorBinderUDA10();
            }

            @Override
            public ServiceDescriptorBinder getServiceDescriptorBinderUDA10() {
                return super.getServiceDescriptorBinderUDA10();
            }

    }
);

Performance problems with UPnP discovery are usually caused by too many XML descriptors, not by their size. This is inherent in the bad design of UPnP; each device may expose many individual service descriptors, and Cling will always retrieve all device metadata. The HTTP requests necessary to retrieve dozens of descriptor files usually outweighs the cost of parsing each.

Note that binders are only used for device and service descriptors, not for UPnP action and event message processing.

Switching XML processors

All control and event UPnP messages have an XML payload, and the control messages are even wrapped in SOAP envelopes. Handling XML for control and eventing is encapsulated in the Cling transport layer, with an extensible service provider interface:

org.fourthline.cling.transport.spi.SOAPActionProcessor
This processor reads and writes UPnP SOAP messages and transform them from/to ActionInvocation data. The protocol layer, on top of the transport layer, handles ActionInvocation only.
org.fourthline.cling.transport.spi.GENAEventProcessor
This processor reads and writes UPnP GENA event messages and transform them from/to a List<StateVariableValue>.

For the SOAPActionProcessor, the following implementations are bundled with Cling Core:

org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.SOAPActionProcessorImpl (default)
This implementation reads and writes XML with the JAXP-provided DOM API provided by JDK 6. You do not need any additional libraries to use this processor. However, its strict compliance with the UPnP specification can cause problems in real-world UPnP applications. This processor will produce errors during reading when XML messages violate the UPnP specification. Use it to test a UPnP stack or application for strict specification compliance.
org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.PullSOAPActionProcessorImpl
This processor uses the XML Pull API to read messages, and the JAXP DOM API to write messages. You need an implementation of the XML Pull API on your classpath to use this processor, for example, XPP3 or kXML 2. Compared with the default processor, this processor is much more lenient when reading action message XML. It can deal with broken namespacing, missing SOAP envelopes, and other problems. In UPnP applications where compatibility is more important than specification compliance, you should use this parser.
org.fourthline.cling.transport.impl.RecoveringSOAPActionProcessorImpl
This processor extends the PullSOAPActionProcessorImpl and additionally will work around known bugs of UPnP stacks in the wild and try to recover from parsing failures by modifying the XML text in different ways. This is the processor you should use for maximum compatibility in your application. Furthermore, it let's you handle a failure when reading an XML message easily by overriding the handleInvalidMessage() method, e.g. to create or log an error report.

You can switch XML processors by overriding the UpnpServiceConfiguration:

UpnpService upnpService = new UpnpServiceImpl(
    new DefaultUpnpServiceConfiguration() {

        @Override
        public SOAPActionProcessor getSoapActionProcessor() {
            return new PullSOAPActionProcessorImpl();
        }

    }
);